Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. All right, so today's דף Daf is
דף כ, Daf Chaf, and we will see God willing finishing the
פרק Perek today. We pick up with a little behind, pick up
on the משנה, Mishnah, you set up in the middle. And this
משנה Mishnah is going to last us till the end of the
פרק, Perek, and it's all about laws of טומאה וטהרה. Tumah and
Taharah. So let's take a look. מחצלת קנים גדולה, Machatzelet kanim gedolah,
so we're dealing of course with, this is an issue we've seen
before, of the סכך S'chach has to be made of something that
is not susceptible for טומאה. Tumah. And we've referred before to issues
about mats, and the basic issue with a mat is if a
mat is made for sitting, then it can become טמא tamei because
it's טומאת מדרס Tumat midras particularly a זב Zav and a זבה,
Zavah, if they sit on something that's made as a seat, then
it becomes an אב הטומאה, Av Hatumah, becomes a source of טומאה.
Tumah. But if it's not made for sitting, then first of all,
as a wooden something made out of like of reeds or hemp
or wood, it would require a receptacle, and even the issue of
receptacle aside when it's flat doesn't have a receptacle, but even that
issue aside, I mean other than when it's a seat, if it's
not serving as a seat, in order to become טמא tamei it
has to have a receptacle, but even that issue aside, it would
be primarily made anyway for roofing, and something that's made to be
a roof is not something that can become טמא, tamei, made part
of a structure, and therefore not something that becomes טמא. tamei. So
we have to decide when we're looking at a mat what its
basic purpose is of having been made and whether it is susceptible
or not. And this issue before they started making these, you know,
סוכה Sukkah mats expressly for that purpose with a million הכשרים Hechsherim
on them, you know, the question would be, can I go to
Home Depot and buy one of these, you know, thin flat bamboo
mats? What is their basic purpose? Is their purpose as a wall
hanging? Is their purpose for roofing? Is their purpose for sitting? You
know, what? I don't know. So what? And what do you do
if it's made generically? Like, you know, the manufacturers say just well,
we know that there's a demand for this. Do they really care
what people use them for? You know, do you go by the
majority of usage? How do you determine, you know, whether it is
a כלי Kli that is מקבל טומאה Mekabel Tumah or not? So
our משנה Mishnah looks at that question. Let's take a look.
Rabbi, does this, a quick question about a pillow that gave a
receptacle when you sit in it and then it goes away when
you get up, what is that?
Yeah, that would not be, that's not structurally having a receptacle. But
again, but something like a pillow that you sit on it is
מקבל טומאה Mekabel Tumah because of מדרס, Midras, particularly a זב Zav
and a זבה, Zavah, because of מדרס, Midras, the טומאת זב וזבה.
Tumat Zav and Zavah. Well, the other issue is something that's flat
like that's wide and flat and that can support things not because
it has a receptacle but just because like a surface. Like a
table. Exactly. So those things are טמא tamei as well, probably only
Rabbinically, but they are as well. Let's take a look at the
משנה. Mishnah. And a mat, a mat could be that also. So
the משנה Mishnah now in middle of דף יט עמוד ב. Daf
Yud Tet Amud Bet. מחצלת קנים גדולה, Machatzelet kanim gedolah, so you
have a reed mat that is large. עשאה לשכיבה, Asah l'shchivah, if
you made it for the purpose of reclining, sitting on it, lying
on it, מקבלת טומאה mekabelet tumah then it can receive טומאה, tumah,
ואין מסככין בה ve'ein mesachchin bah you can't use it for סכך.
S'chach. לסיכוך, L'sichuch, if you made it for סכך s'chach purposes or
you know, not even סוכה Sukkah סכך s'chach purposes, just roofing purposes,
מסככין בה mesachchin bah ואינה מקבלת טומאה, ve'einah mekabelet tumah, you can
use it for סכך s'chach and it's not it's not
it does not become טמא tamei of course. Okay, those are like
two obvious cases, expressly for this or expressly for that. The obvious
key question is let's say it does not have an express purpose,
then how do you define it? Which is going to be what
the גמרא Gemara asks. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר, omer, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says אחת קטנה ואחת גדולה, achas ktanah ve'achas gedolah,
whether a small one or big one, עשאה לשכיבה asah l'shchivah מקבלת
טומאה mekabelet tumah ואין מסככין בה, ve'ein mesachchin bah, if it's for
reclining then it can become טמא tamei and you don't use it
for can't use it for סכך. s'chach. לסיכוך L'sichuch מסככין בה mesachchin
bah ואינה מקבלת טומאה, ve'einah mekabelet tumah,
you can use it for סכך s'chach and it cannot become טמא.
tamei. Again, clearly he's adding something because he says oh, what you
just said doesn't only apply to a big one, it applies to
a small one at all as well. By the way, just let
you know, the basic assumption is that the bigger something is, the
less it's made for personal use and the more it's made for
construction purposes, you know, or for being part of your of your
structure. Therefore a small one naturally is more is more going to
be assumed to be made for the purposes of reclining and more
likely to be considered susceptible. I don't know how big, no, we're
not going on that basis. Anyway, so clearly he's coming but but
still the point is, he's adding the idea of small, but they're
dealing with extremes, they're dealing with express purposes, it's not so clear
what's going on here, which is what the גמרא Gemara comes to
discuss. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. When you say קנים גדולה, kanim gedolah, is that referring to
מחצלת machatzelet גדולה? gedolah?
No, the מחצלת machatzelet is גדולה. gedolah. Okay. So הגופא
קשיא, hagufa kashya, this is an internal internally contradictory. אמרת Amarta עשאה
לשכיבה asah l'shchivah מקבלת טומאה mekabelet tumah ואין מסככין בה, ve'ein mesachchin
bah, you said when you made it for reclining it could become
טמא tamei and you can't use it for סכך. s'chach. טעמא דעשאה
לשכיבה, Ta'ama d'asah l'shchivah, the reason is because you expressly made it
for reclining, that puts it in the vessel category. סתמא, Stama, if
you did it without any express purpose, לסיכוך, l'sichuch, I would have
assumed it's made for סכך s'chach or for made for you know
roofing purposes and it's not a problem. So only when
you expressly... טעמא דעשאה לסכך *Ta'ama d'asa'ah l'schach*, the
reason that it is acceptable is because it was made for סכך
sechach. *s'chach*, it was made for roofing. הסתמא *Hastama*, but if it
was not made with anything, it was made unexpressed, לשכיבה lishchiva *l'shichiva*,
I would say that it's being used, it would be used for
reclining. So you gave me the two extremes, you didn't tell me
what the סתמא *stama* case was. And rather than just saying you
didn't tell me, it says it even in even stronger terms. It's
implicitly contradictory in terms of what the סתמא *stama* case is. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, הא לא קשיא Lo kashya, *ha lo
kashya*, that's not difficult. כאן בגדולה כאן בקטנה *Kan b'gedola kan b'ktana*.
The difference between the first half of the משנה mishna. *Mishnah* and
the second half of the opening line is a big one and
a small
one, meaning if it's a big one, מחצלת machatzelet, קנים kanim, גדולה
gedola, *machatzeles kanim gedola*, if it's a big one, then we assume
a big one is made for roofing. However, if you made it
לשכיבה lishchiva *l'shichiva*, then it's מקבל טומאה Mekabel Tuma *mekabel tumah*. Then
if you made it for reclining, then it's a vessel. And then
the next line, which is referring to now a קטנה ketana *ktana*,
and it's that tiny little important point, but then it's shifting gears
and saying, and if it's a קטנה ketana *ktana*, then you assume
that it's made for reclining, but if you make it for סכך
sechach. *s'chach*, it's okay. So basically, yes, it's contradictory, but the first
case is talking about a גדולה gedola, *gedola*, as it says explicitly.
The second case is talking about a קטנה ketana, *ktana*. A גדולה
gedola *gedola*, the סתמא *stama* is made for סכך sechach. *s'chach*. A
קטנה ketana *ktana*, the סתמא *stama* is made for reclining. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* goes on. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, אומר
*Rabbi Eliezer omer*, let's see if that works in the second part
of the משנה mishna, *Mishnah*. Rabbi Eliezer says, אחת קטנה ketana. ואחת
גדולה gedola *achas ktana v'achas gedola*, whether small or big, עשאה לשכיבה
lishchiva, מקבלת טומאה mekabeles tumah ואין מסככין בה mesachchin bah, *asa'ah l'shichiva
mekabeles tumah v'ein misachachin ba*. So if you made it for reclining,
it becomes, it's a vessel and it's טמא tamei *tamei* or susceptible.
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, טעמא דעשאה לשכיבה *ta'ama d'asa'ah l'shichiva*, the only
reason it's considered to be susceptible for טומאה tumah *tumah* is you
made it for reclining. הסתמא לסכך *Hastama l'schach*. Again, in רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*, the opening statement, that if you make it
for reclining it's a problem,
implies that when it's not expressly made for a particular purpose, it's
made for סכך sechach, *s'chach* or it's acceptable for סכך sechach. *s'chach*.
אימא סיפא *Eima seifa*, look at the second line of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*. עשאה לסכך מסככין בה mesachchin bah, *Asa'ah l'schach
misachachin ba*, if you made it for סכך sechach. *s'chach*, then you
can use it for סכך sechach. *s'chach*, ואינה מקבלת טומאה mekabeles tumah.
*v'eina mekabeles tumah*, and it's not susceptible. טעמא דעשאה לסכך הסתמא לשכיבה
*Ta'ama d'asa'ah l'schach hastama l'shichiva*. The reason is that you made it
for סכך sechach. *s'chach*, but if you didn't say anything expressly, it
would be made for reclining. So still you have a contradiction. Meaning,
why is it a problem more in רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi
Eliezer*? Because רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* expressly says, whether גדולה
gedola *gedola* or קטנה ketana. *ktana*. The rabbi says, or the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma *Tanna Kamma* says, okay, גדולה gedola *gedola*, it starts
by saying גדולה gedola. *gedola*, right? And then it says, if you
make it גדולה לשכיבה gedola lishchiva *gedola l'shichiva*, so then it is
no good, I mean for סכך S'chach. *s'chach*. And it says, for
סכך S'chach. *s'chach*, it is okay, it's good for סכך S'chach, *s'chach*,
right? That's what it says. So the problem is, well what about
the סתמא *stama* case that you didn't make it for either? So
let's just for a minute. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*
says, whether גדולה Gedola, או קטנה ketana, *gedola o ktana*, like לשכיבה
*l'shichiva*
no good,
and לסכך *l'schach* good. Okay, so first of all, you don't even
know what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma. *Tanna Kamma* says by קטנה
ketana. *ktana*. He's throwing in a קטנה *ktana*. But anyway, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, what about the סתמא *stama* case? What about the
middle case, right? You're not telling me the middle case. So it
solves the part by the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma *Tanna Kamma* because
it says, well you're really missing in the opening here is the
implicit point that we're talking about when we talk about here, we're
talking about a קטנה *ktana*. Okay, that sort of solves it. Okay,
so this says, גדולה לשכיבה gedola lishchiva *gedola l'shichiva* is no good,
so the סתמא *stama*, right, the סתמא *stama*, סתמא *stama*, unexpressed, is
good because it's גדולה Gedola, *gedola*, it's made for סכך S'chach. *s'chach*.
The קטנה *ktana* for סכך S'chach. *s'chach* is good, the סתמא *stama*
is no good because the קטנה *ktana* is made for reclining. Okay,
two different cases, so we stuck in the word קטנה *ktana*. But
it doesn't work here, because here he says whether גדולה Gdula. או
קטנה *gedola o ktana*, for לשכיבה *l'shichiva* no good and for לסכך
*l'schach* is good. So you still don't know what the story is
with the סתמא *stama* case, right? Or the way the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says it, more than you don't know, it's implicitly contradictory. This
suggests that the סתמא *stama* case is good, this suggests that the
סתמא *stama* case is not good. So what's the story?
It could be the timing also of the fact that if you're
doing it near סוכות Sukkos *Sukkot*, then סתמא *stama*, that could be.
That could be. Okay, so let's take a look. אלא אמר רבא
amar Rava: *Ella amar Rava*, so we still have a problem, and
certainly in רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* you can't throw in
the idea that we're talking about a different case. אלא אמר רבא
*Ella amar Rava*, so rather רבא *Rava* says, בגדולה כולי עלמא לא
פליגי דסתמא לסכך *b'gedola kulei alma lo pligi d'stama l'schach*. A גדולה
Gdula, *gedola*, nobody disagrees that it's made for סכך S'chach. *s'chach*. By
the way, סכך S'chach. *s'chach* again does not mean for the purpose
of סוכה sukka, *sukkah* necessarily. It means it's made for roofing. Okay?
And therefore everybody agrees that a גדולה Gdula *gedola* is not made
for sitting and it's always good. כי פליגי בקטנה *Ki pligi b'ktana*,
the debate is a קטנה *ktana*. תנא קמא Tanna Kamma סבר קטנה
לשכיבה *Tanna Kamma
savar ktana l'shichiva*. תנא קמא Tanna Kamma *Tanna
Kamma* holds that a small one is made for reclining, right? Like
we said here, we said that קטנה *ktana* implicitly, like it still
might be the way רש״י *Rashi* understands it holding by putting in
this word קטנה *ktana*. So קטנה *ktana* implicitly is going to be
for reclining and only when you make it explicitly for סכך S'chach.
*sechach* it's good. Okay, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer סבר סתם קטנה
stam ketana נמי לסכך *Rabbi Eliezer savar stam ktana nami l'sechach*. And
a סתם stam קטנה *stam ktana* is also for סכך S'chach, *sechach*.
והכי קאמר *V'hachi ka'amar*, and here's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi
Eliezer* is saying back. מחצלת machatzelet, קטנים דאורייתא היא דמתניתא *Machatzat ktanim
d'oreita hi d'matnita*. מחצלת Machatzelet, קטנים גדולה עשאה לשכיבה מקבלת טומאה mekabeles
tumah. ואין מסככין בה *Machatzat ktanim gedola asaa l'shichiva mekabelet tumah v'ein
mesachchin bah*. A big one, if you make it expressly or explicitly
for reclining, then it's a vessel and you can't use it for
סכך S'chach. *sechach*. טעמא דעשאה לשכיבה *Taama d'asaa l'shichiva*, it's only because
you make it explicitly for reclining, הא סתם stam, *ha stam*, without
any expressed intention, נעשה כמי שעשאה לסכך מסככין בה *naaseh k'mi sheasaa
l'sechach mesachchin bah*, then it's like you made it for סכך S'chach.
*sechach* and you can use it for סכך schach, *sechach*. So what
it sort of reads is,
rather than holding that the word קטנה *ktana* is לסכך *l'sechach*, it
leaves it like this.
It leaves it: גדולה *gedola* if you made it לשכיבה *l'shichiva* it's
no good. But, everybody here with me, hit me with an אביי
*Abaye*, but סתם stam *stam*, if you made it סתם stam *stam*,
then that is לסכך *l'sechach* and it's מסככין בה *mesachchin bah*. Okay,
that's sort of the trick it does. If it's לשכיבה *l'shichiva* it's
no good, anything else is considered to be like you made it
לסכך *l'sechach* and it's good. That's the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma *Tanna
Kamma*. So the basic emphasis is that a גדולה סתם gedola stam
*gedola stam* is good.
And a קטנה סתם ketana stam *ktana stam*,
and a קטנה *ktana*, the implicitly would be, right, that a קטנה
*ktana* would be סתם stam שכיבה sechiva *stam shichiva* and no good.
ואתא רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer למימר *V'ata Rabbi Eliezer l'meimar*, and רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* is saying, אחת קטנה ואחת גדולה *achat
ktana v'achat gedola*, whether small or big, סתמה כשירה לסכך *stama kshera
l'sechach*. So then he is saying, whether big or whether big or
small, or small or big, we'll get to that in a minute,
right? He is saying that only if it's לשכיבה *l'shichiva* is it
no good, but again, סתם stam *stam* becomes like it's לסכך *l'sechach*
and good. So that leads very nicely, right? The words that are
basically saying is the second part of the משנה mishna, *Mishnah* where
they say לסכך *l'sechach* is good is a way of saying everything
else is good. Okay? So the תנא Tana *Tanna* says a גדולה
לשכיבה *gedola l'shichiva* is no good, everything else is good, but that's
only by a גדולה *gedola*, קטנה *ktana* would be a problem if
it was סתם stam *stam*. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *Rabbi Eliezer* says
no, whether גדולה *gedola* or קטנה *ktana*, only לשכיבה *l'shichiva* is no
good, everything else is good. Okay, so לסכך *l'sechach* effectively becomes everything
else.
Okay? And it becomes a very easy debate, okay? The תנא *Tanna*
is saying only by a גדולה *gedola* is it generally good, okay?
Right? Only by a גדולה *gedola*, only if it's explicit שכיבה sechiva
*shichiva* is it no good, but generally a גדולה *gedola* is good.
And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* says גדולה *gedola* or קטנה
*ktana* generally it's good. It would only have to be expressly no.
Is there anything else?
Everything else by גדולה *gedola*.
That's what I mean, all other intent.
Okay, but by רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* it really is
everything else.
Well, because he explicitly said קטנה *ktana*. Okay, so anyway, so the
way we solve it, which is a very nice read of the
משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*, is that the second part לסכך *l'sechach* doesn't literally
mean it has to be לסכך *l'sechach*. It means in when it's
anything other than לשכיבה *l'shichiva* it's going to be good. So the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma *Tanna Kamma* says by גדולה *gedola*, only by
גדולה *gedola* is it generally good. And רבי Rebbi אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*
says no, whether גדולה *gedola* or קטנה *ktana*, it's generally good and
it only becomes a problem when you make it לשכיבה *l'shichiva*.
And now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* tries to throw in something like
מר כי אתרא מר *Mar ki atra Mar*...
alright well let's take a look. You know what, we're going to
get confusing enough so we don't need to add that. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אמר אביי *Amar Abaye*, so
that seems to be a beautiful explanation. We treat the second case
in the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* to be לאו דוקא *lav davka* essentially
and the debate is whether the generally assumed good status is only
by the גדולה *gedola* or by גדולה *gedola* and קטנה *ktana*. אמר
אביי *Amar Abaye*, said אביי *Abaye*, אי הכי *ei hachi*, if that's
true, רבי Rebbi אליעזר אומר אחת קטנה ואחת גדולה *Rabbi Eliezer omer
achat ktana v'achat gedola*, he says whether small or big, he should
have said אחת גדולה ואחת קטנה מיבעי ליה *achat gedola v'achat ktana
miba'lei*, whether big or small. Meaning if you...
and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has it that way.
I know, so there's a whole issue here, רש״י *Rashi* and תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot* switching exactly what the גירסא *girsa* is and what the
more
appropriate grammatical way it would have been for the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
to have said it, okay? So our version has it that רבי
Rebbi? אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* is saying
whether it's small or big it generally is good, okay?
And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says he should have said whether it's
big, like you say, or even if it's small, it's okay the
same way. Okay, that's what he should have said. But some have
it that actually no, that that actually would and I don't want
to go back. Anyway, there's a whole debate of רש״י *Rashi* and
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* what the גירסא *girsa* in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is and what the better grammatical way to have said it would
have been if you were coming to make the point, not only
is the big okay, even the small is okay. But the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* thinks that a, there's a grammatical issue of how he
should have phrased it. Number one. ועוד *V'od*, let's not worry about
that too much because there's a lot of rewriting of the text
here and... And you got the point that some are just saying
it should have been neither A nor B, or not only A
even B. The order would have mattered if you were making that
point. ועוד כי פליגי בגדולה Kee pleegee beegdola, פליגי, but more to
the point, I'll show you based on a ברייתא braita that רבי
Rebbi's אליעזר, it's not they're debating the small one. The תנא קמא
says the small one is a problem, and רבי Rebbi. אליעזר is
saying the small one is okay. No, they're debating the status of
a big one. רבי אליעזר לחומרא, Rabbi Eliezer l'chumra, and רבי אליעזר
is being stringent. You wanted to have רבי אליעזר being being Mr.
Lenient and coming along and saying even a small one is okay
if it's the סתם stam case. That's not true. In the ברייתא
braita we see that רבי אליעזר is debating the big one and
being more stringent than the תנא קמא. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in
the ברייתא, braita, and this hopefully will cast some light on what's
going on in our
משנה. Mishnah, מחצלת הקנים. Machatzeles hakanim. Okay, if you've got again a
mat reed, a reed mat, a reed
mat.
רבי אליעזר אומר בגדולה מסככין בה, Rabbi Eliezer omer begdola mesachchin bah,
you can use it for סכך. schach. So that's a clear case
of סתם, Stam right? It didn't say what purpose you made it,
just says a mat a reed mat, you can use it for
סכך. schach, So סתם Stam, you can use it for סכך. schach
רבי אליעזר אומר אם אינה מקבלת טומאה מסככין בה. Rabbi Eliezer omer
im einah mekabeles tumah mesachchin bah. Only if it's not מקבלת טומאה
mekabeles tumah can you use it for סכך, schach which is a
funny thing to respond because we all agree to that principle that
it has to not be מקבלת טומאה. tumah. So presumably what רבי
אליעזר means is, it's not you can't assume it's not מקבלת טומאה.
tumah Only when it's expressly not מקבלת טומאה tumah can you use
it for סכך. So the תנא קמא's saying a סתם case of
a mat reed is a problem, you can assume is okay, and
רבי אליעזר says a big one and רבי אליעזר says no it
has to be a special case. So must be that way. I
don't know, it's funny. אלא אמר רב פפא בקטנה כולי עלמא לא
פליגי דסתם לשכיבה. Ela amar Rav Pappa bekitana kuli alma lo pleegee
destam lishchiva. Fine. So we have to reverse it. We have to
say that by a small one, everybody agrees that that basically is
not good, that that's made for reclining without unless you expressly make
it for a different purpose. כי פליגי בגדולה, the debate is a
big one. תנא קמא סבר סתם גדולה לסיכוך, Tanna Kamma savar stam
gedola leseechuch, the big one can be assumed to be for סכך.
ורבי אליעזר סבר סתם גדולה נמי לשכיבה, Verabbi Eliezer savar stam gedola
nami lishchiva, no, even a big one, we assume it's for reclining
unless you expressly make it for סכך. ומאי עשויה לשכיבה דקאמר? Umai
asuya lishchiva dika'amar? What does he mean when you made it for
reclining, it's it's no good? הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, here's what he
means. סתם עשייתה נמי לשכיבה, Stam asiyasa nami lishchiva, a big one
is assumed to be for the purpose of reclining, עד דעביד לסיכוך,
ad de'avid leseechuch, unless you make it expressly for the purpose of
סכך. So this is a much harder read.
You should do it next to it as opposed to what? Can
you do it next to it? Yeah, alright, go into the other.
I need another color. So רבי אליעזר in general is מחמיר machmir
with סוכה, sukka. right? You have to eat every meal in the
סוכה. sukka. Oh, that's interesting.
Yeah, I don't know
if that translates into the structure of the סוכה. sukka. My שיטה
shita is מחמיר, machmir, you'll have to see if that translates into
the structure of סוכה. Sukkah Okay, so what the way the גמרא
Gemara reads it is the following: is that everybody says a קטנה
is no good, okay? A קטנה is whatever. The תנא קמא is
implicitly, he's talking about a גדולה, but implicitly he's saying a קטנה
סתם ketana stam is no good, okay? So this can read the
way it is: that a גדולה סתם gedola stam is good, a
קטנה סתם ketana stam is not, but this can sort of read
the current way. That we're not changing that. A גדולה, a סתם
גדולה, stam gedola, I'm just gonna use the language of the
גמרא. Gemara
Okay, so the תנא קמא says a גדולה לשכיבה is no good,
a סתם גדולה stam gedola is good, and a קטנה סתם ketana
stam is no good. Okay. לרבי אליעזר, LeRabbi Eliezer, we are now
saying everybody agrees that a סתם קטנה is no good. רבי אליעזר's
going to be even more strict by גדולה. So he says whether
גדולה or קטנה, he's responding to implicitly what the תנא קמא saying
that a קטנה סתם ketana stam is no good. He says you
say a קטנה is no good, even a גדולה is like a
קטנה. The same way a קטנה סתם ketana stam is no good,
even a גדולה's like a קטנה. And therefore, any if there now
this is where it gets tricky, לשכיבה really means every case, every
case or every סתם case,
any
סתם case is like לשכיבה and therefore no good. And the only
case that is going to be good is going to be when
it is לסיכוך. leseechuch. Okay? So it's a very hard read. The
תנא קמא says a גדולה לשכיבה is no good, which means the
סתם is good. So גדולה סתם Gedola Stam is good, implicitly קטנה
סתם Ktana Stam is no good. רבי אליעזר says whether גדולה or
קטנה, meaning a גדולה is just like a קטנה. And therefore, every
case a סתם case is like לשכיבה, no good. And the only
case that's good is going to be לסיכוך. leseechuch. It's a very,
very hard read of the משנה, mishna but according to this, or
it would be the only, according to this, the one that really
means what he says is the phrase that means it is the
first phrase, גדולה. And then when you get to רבי אליעזר, the
phrase that's being precise is the second phrase, לסיכוך. leseechuch. Okay, so
it's a very hard read of the משנה, mishnah but we're doing
it. really the better read was what we said before, I think,
but you know, but the גמרא Gemara is doing it to reconcile
it with the ברייתא. Baraita. Okay, so fine, so according to one
version, everybody agrees that a גדולה סתם Gedola Stam is good, and
רבי אליעזר is being lenient in saying even a קטנה סתם Ktana
Stam is good, and this is the mirror image of that. Everybody
agrees that a קטנה סתם is no good, and they're debating whether
a גדולה סתם is good or not. All right. You're going to
be tested on all of this tomorrow. Now let's take a look.
תנא the רישא Reisha is like this. I should go first. Oh
yeah? All right. I did get it, so I'm in class. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay. Okay, where?
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
מחצלות של שיפה ושל גמי. Machatzlot shel Shaifa v'shel Gemi. So now
we can sort of put aside the exact משנה. We're still going
to deal with the same issue, but we don't have to fit
it into the משנה, but we'll be dealing with the same types
of questions. So if you have a mat of שיפה Shaifa and
גמי, Gemi, can people tell me what that is?
Papyrus and bullrushes.
Papyrus and bullrushes. There you go. Okay, so that is, okay, so
that is something that, I don't know, do you know what a
bullrush is?
There's a picture here.
Okay. Anyway, those are soft. What? Water type plant.
Water type plant.
Wonderful. Those are soft materials, so those are more likely to be
for reclining, and they're more likely to be, you know, מקבל טומאה
mekabel tumah. and not usable for סכך. So you have a mat
of שיפה וגמי, Shaifa v'Gemi, גדולה, if it's big, מסככין בה, you
can use it for סכך. So this is nice. It talks about
what the סתם case is, because that's really all we have to
know. Tell me the סתם, and when you, when you do it
explicitly, that'll be whatever you say. So this, if it's made big,
it's, it's, you can use it for סכך, even though it's soft,
when it's big, it's made for roofing. קטנה אין מסככין בה, Ktana
ein mesachchin bah, when it's small it's made for sitting and you
can't use it for סכך. That is nice. של קנים ושל חילת,
Shel kanim v'shel chilat, if it's however reeds and חילת, chilat, something
else, which is harder, and therefore less likely to be for sitting,
גדולה מסככין בה, Gedola mesachchin bah, if it's big you can use
it for סכך. That's obvious. Even a soft one, if it's big
you can use it. If it's small, there might still be cases
that it's assumed to be for סכך. Now if it's small, it
depends how it is manufactured. ארוגה אין מסככין בה, Aruga ein mesachchin
bah, if it is, I'm sorry, I didn't, it was not גדולה,
it was גדולה. Oy, this is very, as if it weren't confusing
enough. Okay, so של שיפה ושל גמי. Shel Shaifa v'shel Gemi. Now
and now we're talking about a small one of שיפה וגמי, Shaifa
v'Gemi, of this harsher material, because obviously a big one is going
to be good. If the big one of the soft material is
good, a big one of the harsher material is good. But now
we're talking about a small one of the harsher material. If it's
גדולה, which means like גדילים תעשה לך, Gedilim ta'aseh lecha, okay, they
just had to do that to confuse you. So if basically it
is made as a type of a basket weave is what גדולה
means. So that's like, you know, that's like less soft, it's a
little, you know, it's harsher that way. So then you can, even
a small one, מסככין בה, you can use it for סכך. ארוגה,
Aruga, however, if it is small and tightly woven, then it'll be
softer maybe, maybe used thinner strands of it, and אין מסככין בה,
ein mesachchin bah, you can't use it for סכך. Okay, so you
got it? If it's the softer material, big you can use, small
you can never use. If it's the harsher material, then small it
depends how it's woven. A basket weave you can use, it's not
made for sitting. A, a tighter sort of weave you can't use,
it is made for sitting. רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי אומר משום אביו,
Rabbi Yishmael Berabbi Yosi omer mishum aviv, אחת זו ואחת זו מסככין
בה. achat zo v'achat zo mesachchin bah.
He says in either case you can use it for סכך, once
it's the harsher material, even a smaller one you can use for
סכך. Okay. וכן היה רבי דוסא אומר כדבריו, V'chen hayah Rabbi Dosa
omer k'divarav,
and רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa used to say like רבי ישמעאל ברבי
יוסי Rabbi Yishmael Berabbi Yosi that when it's made out of this
harsher material, even the small one you can use for סכך.
Does רבי אליעזר agree with all of these distinctions?
We, I don't know, right? The גמרא Gemara does not map this
onto רבי אליעזר והחכמים Rabbi Eliezer v'hachachamim and I'm not going to
try. Okay. תנן התם, Tnan hatam, now we taught over there in
עדיות. Eduyot. כל החוצלות, Kol hachutzlot, which sounds like מחצלות, machatzlot, מחצלת,
machatzelet. right? But there's going to be a question:
is it like מחצלות?
machatzlot? Well right, or so מחצלת, no it's the same order, חוצלות
מחצלות. chutzlot machatzlot. Is it like מחצלות? machatzlot? מחצלת, I know. So
the question is what is חוצלות chutzlot as distinct from מחצלת. So
we're going to see. But it's something like that. So all these
חוצלות, chutzlot, מטמאין טמא מת, metam'in tmei meit, can become, can have
the טומאה tumah of a dead body, meaning can are, are susceptible
for טומאה. tumah דברי רבי דוסא. Divrei Rabbi Dosa. רבי דוסא, Rabbi
Dosa, remember we just quoted רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa before. וחכמים אומרים,
V'chachamim omrim, מדרס. midras. It can become טמא מדרס tmei midras of
seats. So the גמרא Gemara says מדרס, midras, meaning you use it
to sit on, a זב zav or זבה zava can use it
to sit on and it gets the טומאה tumah of seats. So
the גמרא Gemara says מדרס אין טמא מת לא? Midras in, tmei
meit lo? What? Only the טומאה tumah of seats and not the
טומאה tumah of a dead body? והאנן תנן, V'ha-anan tnan, we taught
in the משנה, כל המטמא מדרס מטמא טמא מת, Kol hametamei midras
metamei tmei meit, anything that can become have the טומאה tumah of
seats can have the טומאה of a dead body. Now that's An
important principle because you, because
in theory you would have said that's not the case. Meaning, let's
say I told you here's a flat wood mat, okay? Can it
become טמא tamei, with טומאת מת? tumas meis? So if you've been
learning for a while, you know the הלכה halacha is that פשוטי
כלי עץ peshutei klei eitz are not מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. A
wood vessel that doesn't have a receptacle cannot become טמא, tamei your
answer would be no. But I would say but look, it can
become טמא tamei. if a זב zav or זבה zavah sits on
it because it's a seat, right? And anything that functions as a
seat can be טומאת מדרס tumas midras if a זב zav or
זבה zavah sits on it. So once it's considered a seat and
a vessel for the laws of מדרס, midras, it also is a
vessel for the laws of טמאי מת tmei meis and even that
can become טמא. tamei So that first of all is a חידוש
chiddush that most people even if they're aware about the כלים keilim
or whatever aren't aware that the rule that for example a wood
vessel without a receptacle can't be טמא tamei is with an asterisk
unless it's a seat. If it's a seat, what's a seat? Something
that functions and is made for that purpose and is generally used
for that purpose, then it is a בענץ, bentz, a wood chair,
not your table, that because it's made for sitting it can become
טמא tamei for a זב zav and זבה, zavah, it can be
a טמאי מת. tmei meis. So anything that's a מדרס midras can
become for טמאי מת. tmei meis. It's not the reverse. What's something
that could be טמא tamei for טמאי מת tmei meis but not
become טמא tamei for מדרס? midras? It's it's simple if you think
about it a minute. It could become טמא tamei. if a מת
meis touches it but not if a זב zav or זבה zavah
sits on it. Anything that's not a seat.
Right?
Let's say you have, right, let's say you have your wooden spoon,
right? So any wood vessel, right, that is not a seat can
become טמאי מת tmei meis that has a בית קיבול beis kibul
can become טמאי מת tmei meis without being טומאת מדרס. tumas midras.
But there are but anything that is considered a seat, a טומאת
מדרס, tumas midras, can also be טמאי מת. tmei meis. So your
table would be your table would be טמאי מת, tmei meis, well
it doesn't have a receptacle, so but let's talk for now I
mean we'll get to that in a minute, but okay let's just
talk about your your wooden spoon, right, can be טמאי מת tmei
meis without being מדרס. midras. So this משנה is talking about a
mat. So the issue is the following. Everybody is going if the
mat can become a is used as a seat, obviously it could
be טמאי מת. tmei meis. So the one that says מדרס midras
means מדרס midras and טמאי מת. tmei meis. The one that says
only טמאי מת tmei meis means yes I'll concede it's a receptacle
but it's not made for sitting, this mat is made for something
else, for roofing or whatever. So this then becomes the debate. If
you say מדרס midras you acknowledge it as a seat, and if
you say מת meis you don't acknowledge it as made for sitting,
okay? So let's take a look.
Is there a difference between the terms שכיבה sechiva and מדרס? midras?
No. שכיבה sechiva? is same thing. Yeah, טומאת מדרס tumas midras is
the category. שכיבה sechiva is what purpose it was made for. But
the category of טומאה there's טומאת מת tumas meis and there's מדרס
midras and there's טומאת שרץ tumas sheretz and there's
טומאת נבלה. tumas neveilah.
טומאת מדרס tumas midras is שכיבה? Right. שכיבה describes what you're doing
with it
but it goes with מדרס.
midras. Exactly, exactly.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says: אימא אף מדרס. Eima af midras.
So even מדרס. midras. So now we have חכמים chachamim saying that
this mat is made for sitting and רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa because
it can become טמאי מדרס tmei midras and רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa
says it's not made for sitting. Now the interesting thing though I
should alert you to, which is we're going to have to worry
about is besides this debate of which types of mats are made
for sitting, until now we've assumed that any mat not made for
sitting is what? Roofing.
Is
roofing and therefore not מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah, Here you have רבי
דוסא Rabbi Dosa saying this mat is not made for sitting but
it's still able to become טמא. tamei, Right? You see that point
there? Right, we for us it was so far it was an
either or. Either for roofing and therefore unable to, either for sitting
and therefore able to become טמא, tmei the alternative was roofing and
you're in the clear. Here we have that even if it's not
made for sitting it's still some type of a vessel. So we're
going to have to worry about that. But let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. Okay, מאי חוצלות? mai chotzloth? So the first thing
we have to worry about is what is this חוצלות. chotzloth. So
אמר רב אבדימי בר חמדורי amar Rav Avdimi bar Hamduri מרזובלי. Marzuvli.
Oh, it's מרזובלי. Marzuvli. To which the גמרא Gemara. says thanks that
helped a lot. מאי מרזובלי? Mai marzuvli? What's מרזובלי? marzuvli? For אמר
רבא: מזבלי, Mazvli, which we will say thanks that helped a lot
but the גמרא Gemara still assumes it knows what it is, which
basically רש"י Rashi says it means that it's a type of a
thing that is used for a pillow purpose, okay? And presumably different
than a normal mat because it might actually be almost like a
sack, something that you can put things in. Wait,
so it's a mat for a pillow? No, the חוצלות. chotzloth. The
חוצלות chotzloth that we're debating whether they're made for sitting or not,
okay? Is a pillow? Is right, is it some doesn't involve reeds?
What? Well, we haven't discussed it at all what material it's made
out of, okay? So anyway it's some type of a pillow which
we might see in a minute also has maybe is more like
a pillowcase has some type of a, you know, contain you know
can be used as somewhat of a sack. That's one interpretation of
the debate. ריש לקיש אומר: Reish Lakish omer: ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says מחצלות ממש. machatzalot mamash. No, it's a mat. ואזל ריש לקיש
לטעמיה, Va'azal Reish Lakish l'taimei, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish goes according to
his reasoning. דאמר ריש לקיש: De'amar Reish Lakish: הריני כפרת Hareini kaparat
Behold, I am the atonement for רבי חייא ובניו. Rebbi Chiyya u-vanav.
Now that's, by the way, an important phrase because the גמרא Gemara
says that after somebody's father or רבי dies, or mother, after a
person's parent or רבי dies, he's supposed to say הריני כפרת משכבו.
Hareini kapparat mishkavo. I am the atonement
for their
demise, which means that anything bad that happens to me should atone
for any sins that they have had. And it's a very best...
as... and
why... because you have children. So if you take a look, רש"י
Rashi refers to that. רש"י Rashi says
where's the רש"י? Rashi? Right, three lines from the bottom of the
long line. הריני כפרת יסורין הבאים עלי לכפרתו, Hareini kapparat yissurin habaim
alai l'chapparatov, those should count to the atonement of רבי חייא ובניו.
Rebbi Chiyya u-vanav. הוא לשון כבוד הוא זה כשמזכיר אביו ורבו אחר
מיתתו צריך לומר כן. Hu lashon kavod hu zeh kshe-mazkir aviv v'rabo
achar mitato tzarich lomar ken. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says that
that's the way that a person
after the death of a... I believe the גמרא Gemara, also says
parent, not just father, but I'll double check.
I thought that מיתה עצמה מכפרת mita atzma mechaperet for the person.
Yeah, but not for everything necessarily. Anyway, this is a way of
sort of showing your ongoing sense of responsibility towards them. So, he
is saying, אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, הריני כפרת של רבי
חייא ובניו. Hareini kapparat shel Rebbi Chiyya u-vanav. So just that, that's
just an aside but sort of just fascinating him using that term.
שבתחילה, She-b'tchilla, this is going to be a fascinating little introduction to
a technical law of טומאת טהרה. tumat tara. שבתחילה, She-b'tchilla, כשנשתכחה תורה
מישראל, kshe-nishtachacha torah m'Yisrael, when תורה Torah was forgotten from ישראל, Yisrael,
עלה עזרא מבבל ויסדה. ala Ezra mi-Bavel v'yisdah. עזרא Ezra had to
come from בבל, Bavel, Babylon, and create its foundation, reinstitute תורה. Torah.
After the חורבן הבית? Churban HaBayit? Well, you'll see, no no no,
you'll see where we're going. Okay. After the חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayit,
right, all of the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim were taken out of
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and you needed
עזרא Ezra to come from בבל Bavel to reinstitute it. Now normally
when you say נשתכחה תורה מישראל, nishtachacha torah m'Yisrael, you assume that
we're talking about ישראל Yisrael meaning the Jewish people. But here, it
sounds a little bit like we're talking about ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
because it's always going to be how it had to be reinstituted
from בבל. Bavel. חזרה ונשתכחה, Chazra v'nishtachacha, then it was forgotten again.
עלה הלל הבבלי ויסדה. Ala Hillel HaBavli v'yisdah. הלל Hillel the Babylonian
had to come and reinstitute it, right? We forget that הלל Hillel
originally comes from בבל. Bavel. This was the famous story that they
didn't know if a קרבן פסח korban pesach could be brought on
ערב שבת, erev shabbat, and it says, oh, there's somebody who came
from בבל, Bavel, והלל הבבלי שמו, v'Hillel HaBavli sh'mo, and he'll know
whether you can bring a קרבן פסח korban pesach on ערב שבת.
erev shabbat. Okay, the irony is that הלל הבבלי Hillel HaBavli said
he knew it because he had a דרשה drasha from שמעיה ואבטליון,
Shemaya v'Avtalyon, who were in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. But nevertheless, you
needed a Babylonian to come and to... from Jordan for national... to
reinstitute. חזרה ונשתכחה, Chazra v'nishtachacha, and then it went down again, it
was in decline
again, ועלו רבי חייא ובניו
ויסדוה.
v'alu Rebbi Chiyya
u-vanav v'yisduha. And רבי חייא Rebbi Chiyya
and his children came and reinstituted it, which is quite fascinating. Whatever
happened to רבי? But maybe it means... maybe it means in the
aftermath of רבי's death. רבי חייא Rebbi Chiyya was right after, overlapped
with רבי. Alright, so first of all, that's fascinating, just that little
aside about how we've always needed the Babylonians to come and reinstitute
תורה Torah in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. וכן אמר... V'chen amar... okay,
now that we've got that introduction... exactly... now that we've got that
introduction, let's see what it's all about... what he's trying to say.
וכן אמר רבי חייא ובניו, V'chen amar Rebbi Chiyya u-vanav,
all this was in
order to quote רבי חייא Rebbi Chiyya and his sons. לא נחלקו
רבי דוסא וחכמים Lo nechelku Rebbi Dosa v'chachamim אלא על מחצלאות של
אושא,
ela al machatzalot
shel
Usha, they were not debating the mats from אושא, Usha, שהן טמאות,
shehen tmeiot, those are going to be טמא tamei because those are
so soft, they're always made for sitting. ושל טבריא שהן טהורות, V'shel
Tveria shehen tehorot, nor of טבריא Tveria because those are always טהור,
tahor, those are always harsh and they're made for roofing. על מה
נחלקו? Al mah nechelku? What was the debate? על שאר מקומות, al
shar mekomot, the mats from other places. מר סבר Mar savar כיון
דליכא דיתבי עלייהו keivan d'leika d'yatvi alai כדטבריא דמין. k'd'Tveria damin. One
holds since that people don't sit on it, it's like those of
טבריא Tveria and it's made for roofing or some other purpose and
it's not a problem. ומר סבר U-mar savar כיון דמיקרי ויתבי עלייהו
keivan d'mikrei l'yatvi alai כדאושא דמין. k'd'Usha damin. No, every now and
then people sit on it, it's like the אושא Usha mats, it's
sometimes used. And that's a fascinating question. What do you mean, what
purpose is it serving? Do you go by the majority purpose? Do
you go by the fact that it's included amongst the purposes in
which it's used? And he says, that's what this debate is about,
whether this thing is טומאת מדרס, tumat midras, the fact that as
a rule, as a general rule it's not made for this, but
every now and then you'll take the mat down off of the
roof or off the wall, wherever it is, and you need an
extra seat and you'll sit on it, and is that enough for
טומאת מדרס? tumat midras? That's the debate. But for... but the fact
that he frames it as not the mats of אושא Usha and
not the mats of טבריא Tveria shows you that he's interpreting that
what they're talking about is mats. Yes. Is there something here to
also connect to the interplay between halakhic and aggadic discourse? Yes, אושא
Usha and טבריה Tveria are two places where the סנהדרין Sanhedrin was
located after יבנה. Yavne. Interesting, right. Right. The center of תורה Torah
being reconstituted in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So I don't know, how
does that square with the term from Goshen and whatever? It's connected
to that little... Fascinating, fascinating. Good, good point. Okay, so let's take
a look now what the גמרא Gemara does with all of this.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר מר: Amar Mar:
All the חוצלות khutzlos מטמא טמאי מת. metamei tumei meis. Now we're
going to go back, now that we've introduced the question of what
חוצלות khutzlos means and have this nice little passage from ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish about הרי אני כפרת רבי חייא, Harei ani kaparas Rebbi
Chiya, now we're going to go and try and work through the
ברייתא braisa and see which, you know, how it makes sense and
what's really going on. By the way, you'll remember, right, that I
told you the difference between אמר מר Amar Mar and גופא. Gufa.
אמר מר Amar Mar is we quoted something in full and now
we're going to like analyze it section by section, which is what
we did. We quoted the whole משנה about חוצלות, khutzlos, right, and
now we're going to look at it and figure it all out.
גופא Gufa is we quoted a passage from some text in part
of a discussion to be a to be a prooftext and now
we're going to go back and look at the whole text in
its entirety. Okay, so anyway, אמר מר. Amar Mar. So now let's
go. אמר מר Amar Mar is about the parts that we've read
in the whole... basically... the whole גופא דבר, gufa davar, right. Okay.
אמר מר: Amar Mar: כל החוצלות מטמא טמאי מת דברי רבי דוסא.
Kol hakhutzlos metamei tumei meis divrei Rebbi Dosa. All of them according
to רבי דוסא Rebbi Dosa can be טמאי מת, tumei meis, but
they're not made for sitting. Okay, now again, the interesting thing for
us is we've been assuming that if it's not for sitting you're
golden. It's not a problem. Here we see that it's not for
sitting and it can still be a problem. So let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says: והתניא, Ve-ha tanyah, didn't we teach
in a ברייתא: braisa: וכן היה רבי דוסא אומר כדבריו, Ve-khen haya
Rebbi Dosa omer ke-devarav, רבי דוסא Rebbi Dosa said like his words,
meaning that... that the case before that certain types of mats, right,
if they're made by weave or they're made by whatever קנים, they're
made by... what... reeds. Anyway, reed mats based on the weave and
based on whether, you know, how it's woven. Is it big, is
it small, and so on. That if it's not made for sitting
it's טהור. tahor. So how does he here say that a seat
not made for sitting can still become טמא tamei. if until now
he's been saying and everybody's been saying that a mat not made
for sitting is טהור? tahor? Right? You get the question? Right? For
whatever the issue here is going on, until now we've been assuming
any mat not made for sitting is טהור tahor and here he's
saying this mat is not made for sitting and it's still טמא.
tamei. So what's the story? So the גמרא Gemara, says: לא קשיא,
it's not difficult. הא דאית ליה גדנפא הא דלית ליה גדנפא. Ha
de-is leh gedanpa ha de-leis leh gedanpa. It's whether it has a
rim around it or it doesn't have a rim around it. If
it doesn't have a rim around it, then why is it טהור?
tahor? Because then it is פשוטי כלי עץ. peshutei klei eitz. Right?
It's something like a wood vessel that is... these reeds or whatever
are like wood, are treated like wood for this הלכה, halakha, and
therefore it is טהור. tahor. So therefore if it's not made as
a seat, the alternative is being totally טהור. tahor. Here it has
a rim around it and you can put stuff in it and
it can contain things. And therefore even if it's not a seat,
it's still able to become טמא. tamei. Okay. מתיבי, Mesivei, I'll ask
you on this: חוצלות של שם ושל גמי ושל שק ושל ספירה,
Khutzlos shel sham u-shel gami u-shel sak u-shel safira, if you have
חוצלות, khutzlos, which now we know either means mats or some type
of a pillowcase, and they're made of all of these different types
of material, מטמא טמאי מת דברי רבי דוסא. metamei tumei meis divrei
Rebbi Dosa. רבי דוסא Rebbi Dosa says they can become טמאי מת.
tumei meis. וחכמים אומרים אף מדרס. Va-khachamim omrim af midras. And the
חכמים khachamim say even מדרס. midras. Okay. So what's the problem? בשלמא.
Bi-shlama. So again, why could they be טמאי מת? tumei meis? We'll
say like we've said, it has a rim around it and therefore
even if it's not a seat, it's able to become טמאי מת.
tumei meis. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara bothers the גמרא
Gemara right now. בשלמא למאן דאמר מר זוטרא, Bi-shlama le-man de-amar Mar
Zutra, so I get it if this חוצלות khutzlos are basically like
pillowcases. So שם ושל גמי, sham u-shel gami, I understand how these
things can still become טמא. tamei. If it's made of שם sham
and גמי, gami, which is some type of a softer material, חזו
לקינתא דפירי. khazu le-kinta de-pirei. That you could use it for basically
some type of a sack of fruit, you store fruit in it.
שק ושל ספירה, Shel sak u-shel safira, if it's made of a
sackcloth, חזי לגוקי וצני. khazi le-guki ve-tzani. That's fit for... that, you
know, even containing like beans and flour in it, like even smaller
types of fruit. But whatever it's made out of, if it's a
type of a pillowcase, then you can use it as a container
and I understand why it could still become טמא. tamei. אלא למאן
דאמר מחצירא, Ella man de-amar makh-tzira, but if it's a mat, what
are you going to use a mat for? בשלמא של שק ושל
ספירה, Bi-shlama shel sak u-shel safira, I get if it's of the
sackcloth, it's the softer material, חזו לפרסי ונבסא. khazu le-farsi ve-navsa. It's
fit for, again these are all very strange words, but רש"י Rashi
says this means that you can use it as a type of
a hanging curtain. So here's the interesting thing. Here's the interesting thing.
So here's the interesting thing, this is, right? If you use it
for roofing, it's not מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah. but if you use
it for curtain, it's not considered an actual part of the structure,
it actually is considered a vessel and it is מקבל טומאה. mekabel
tumah That's actually an interesting הלכה. halacha. For example, well let me
give you, well yes, how about the fact that it's פשוטי כלי
עץ pshutei klei etz is an interesting point, I'll get back to,
but first let's understand what type of use you're using for that's
not roofing use. So it's interesting because like by שבת, Shabbat, right,
you cannot make a מחיצה, mechitzah, like we discussed that before, a
wall, right? Can you hang a picture on a wall? So according
to a lot of פוסקים poskim or can you hang a curtain
up? Like according to a lot of פוסקים poskim you can. Those
are not considered part of your structure, they're considered hanging from your
structure. So a picture to some degree I guess, but let's say
you're hanging up like a shower curtain, or a curtain that you
hang up, you can, you're allowed to, you're just putting something on
your wall, you're not making a wall. The nails are already in
the wall. The nails are already in the wall, you're just to
hang it on the rail or hanging up your shower curtain, you're
not making a wall, you're just putting a hanging from your ceiling,
but it's not a wall of the structure. Okay, to me some,
I mean depends on the circumstance, how much does it really become
part of the structure or not, but that's the general פסק psak
is that way that you might that you're allowed to do that.
So this is like this idea, if you're using it as a
curtain, something that's made as part of a structure can't be טמא.
tamei. It has to be a vessel. But saying, oh well, you
can use it as a wall hanging. Oh, if you use it
as a wall hanging or as a curtain then it's a vessel
then it can become טמא. tamei. It's not considered part of a
structure even though you're hanging it as a curtain. Now what about
the fact that it's פשוטי כלי עץ? pshutei klei etz? Okay, so
תוספות Tosafot, says, oh well, first of all, no, for here תוספות
Tosafot says there's a special הלכה halacha that a curtain can become
טמא. tamei. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot חזיין לפרסי, chazyan l'farsi,
תוספות Tosafot says מסך לפני הפתח, masach lifnei hapetach, okay, I think
תוספות Tosafot says that the early word פרסי parsi before meant a
curtain. מקבל טומאה הוא, mekabel tumah hu, כדאמרינן בפרק המביא בביצה k'amrinan
b'perek hamevi b'beitzah מפני מה אמרו וילון טמא. mipnei mah amru vilon
tamei. Okay, so anyway, so תוספות Tosafot. would say that maybe there's
a special that there's a special הלכה halacha that a curtain can
become טמא. tamei But we'll worry about the בית קיבול beit kibul
in a minute. So now the גמרא Gemara first just wants to
figure out what the function is. So let's go back to the
גמרא. Gemara. What you can do on שבת Shabbat becomes מקבל טומאה
mekabel tumah. in a טומאה context. In other words, you can hang
the thing. No, I'm just using it as evidence that it's not
part of the structure, that it's considered a vessel, okay. So the
גמרא says like this. So that I get. So you can use
it for a curtain. So and use it for a curtain then
I get why it can become טמא tamei. and it's not part
of a structure even though it's not a seat. אלא דהוצא ודחלפא
ela d'hutza v'dachalpa when it's made as a harsher material, למאי חזו,
l'mai chazu, what do you use it for? I mean again a
pillowcase we understood you could use to store things, it's like a
sack. But if this is just a mat and it's the harsher
material, what are you going to use it for? So it says
חזו לנזיאתא, chazu l'neziata, it's fit for נזיאתא. neziata. What is נזיאתא?
neziata? So רש"י Rashi says you can use it as a cover
for a barrel. Okay, but תוספות Tosafot says, but then why? It
doesn't have a receptacle. So look at תוספות. Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says
חזיין לנזיאתא, chazyan l'neziata, פירש בקונטרס לכסות בהן גיגיות שעושין בהן שכר.
peresh bakuntres l'chasot bahen gigiyot she'osin bahen shechar. וקשה לומר כן דדהוצא
ודחלפא לא מקבל טומאה אלא מתורת כלי עץ v'kashe lomar ken d'd'hutza
v'dachalpa lo mekabel tumah ela mitorat kli etz דאיתקש לשק d'itkesh l'sak
and it needs to have some type of a בית קיבול. beit
kibul. So the last line of that תוספות says צריך לומר הכא
שעושים לקבל בהם דבר, tzarich lomar hacha she'osim l'kabel bahem davar, it
has some type of a rim and you do use it in
order to be some type of a container, okay. So basically, what
the גמרא is trying to work out this issue, is it a
pillowcase or is it a sack, but again the point here is
that this, even if it's not a seat, can become טמא. tamei
Why? We first have to identify what use it would have other
than roofing. If its only use is roofing, it's not a vessel.
Number two, even if we've identified what use it has, if it's
considered something that's like a פשוטי כלי עץ, pshutei klei etz, it
also has to have a rim. But if it has the use
and it has the rim, then it's מקבל טומאה. mekabel tuma. When
we said, when we said if it's not a mat it's טהור,
tahor, that would be because it didn't have the rim and therefore
it would be טהור. tahor. So a table would never be a
problem then, right? Because it doesn't have a... Well, again, some things
that are big and flat and are made for supporting things would
be טמא at least דרבנן d'rabanan and so a table... yeah, could
become any טומאה of a vessel, but so a table is a
problem. Okay, so the גמרא says like this. Okay, איכא דאמרי, ika
d'amri, some say that have the discussion starting at the opposite end.
בשלמא למאן דאמר מפץ... bishlama l'man d'amar mapatz... I get if it
means a mat. דשל הוצא ודחלפא חזו לנזיאתא. d'shel hutza v'dachalpa chazu
l'neziata. If it's made of the harsher material it can be used
for נזיאתא. neziata. רש"י Rashi says a barrel
cover, תוספות says a container. דשל שק ושל צפיר d'shel sak v'shel
tzafir if it's the softer material חזו לפרסי ונבזתא, chazu l'farsi v'navzata,
that can be used as a curtain. אלא למאן דאמר מרזובלי, ela
l'man d'amar marzubli, but if it's a pillowcase, בשלמא דשל שק ושל
צפיר bishlama d'shel sak v'shel tzafir I get of the softer material
חזו לגוכי וצני. chazu l'guki v'tzanei. Fine, okay, we got the idea.
Okay, it's either a seat and then it's מקבל טומאה. mekabel tuma
If it's not a seat, then it might still be מקבל טומאה
mekabel tuma, if it serves as a vessel and if it has
a rim and is not פשוטי כלי עץ peshutei klei etz or
maybe used as a curtain would have a different status. תניא, Tanya,
אמר רבי חנניה, amar Rabbi Chananya, says Rabbi Chananya, כשרדתי לגולה kesheradeti
lagola when I went down into the exile, מצאתי זקן אחד matzati
zaken echad I found a certain elder, ואמר לי ve'amar li and
he said to me, מסככין בבודיא, mesachchin bebudya, you can make, you
can use for סכך, you can use בודיא, budya, which is a
mat. וכשבאתי אצל רבי יהושע אחי אבא Ucheshbati eitzel Rabbi Yehoshua achi
Abba when I came to Rabbi Yehoshua my uncle, my father's brother,
הודא לדברי hoda lidevbarai that's right, you can use mats for סוכות
again. We're sort of dropping any discussion big, small, what material, maybe
they knew what this בודיא budya was. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav
Chisda, והוא דלית ליה דדנפא, vehu deleit lei dedanpa, but now to
tie it into the previous discussion, not the big, small, or material,
only if it doesn't have a rim. If it has a rim,
then it's מקבל טומאה, it has a בית קיבול. beit kibul. אמר
עולא, Amar Ulla, הני בודיאתא דבני מחוזא, hanei budyata debnei Mechuza, these
mats of the people of Mechuza, אלמלא קיירא שלהן ilmale kiyara shelahen
if it was not their wall, the rim around them, מסככין בהן
mesachchin bahen you could have used them as סכך. תניא נמי הכי,
Tanya nami hachi, we've taught similarly, מסככין בבודיא, mesachchin bebudya, you can
use בודיא budya for סכך, ואם יש להם קיירא ve'im yesh lahem
kiyara if they have a little rim around it, אין מסככין בה
ein mesachchin bah you cannot. Again, fascinating that the end discussion completely
drops the issue of big and small and what material, goes just
straight to does it have a rim or not have a rim.
הדרן עלך סוכה, Hadran alach Sukkah, we still can start the next
paragraph. Yes, Mike. You had an immediate question before, so what about
who defines it, like, you know, is it the end consumer or
is it the manufacturer? Right, yeah. Is that addressed? It's not addressed
in the גמרא, it's addressed elsewhere. I mean, a lot of the
things are that if things are made to be sold, then it
goes, you know, obviously then it goes for what's basically the market
is, you know, and what people use it for. But where's the
individual preference come into play? It might not, it might not. If
you buy it and you intend to use it for something then
and it also has an open-ended purpose, then that might have an
effect to a חומרא. chumra. Okay, but yeah, that is an important
question. Those are the questions before they made these סוכה mats with
הכשרים hechsherim on them, you had the interest, this גמרא became very,
very relevant להלכה. lehalacha. I know, I know, they had the whole,
I would have to review what the literature on that, I don't
remember, but yes, all of those questions are relevant, does the majority
of usage, the minority, you know, sometimes it's like these car things
that you sit on, like, you know, right exactly. That would be
but that would clearly be made for but if I decide I
want to use it for my סכך does it make a difference?
Well if I decide I don't want to sit on it but
I want to use it for my סכך I couldn't because it's
clearly made for like a yeah, those are clearly made for that
particular purpose. So even so I can't divert it from its purpose.
Right. I mean you can but it wouldn't change its status. כל
דבר היורד לידי טומאה במחשבה אין עולה אלא על ידי שינוי מעשה.
Kol davar hayored lidei tuma bemachshava ein oleh ela al yedei shinui
ma'aseh. By the way, here I just want to, yeah, if it's
a neutral construction then that your intention matters. If what? If it's
a neutral construction. Yes, exactly. Correct, like a plank. Yep. By the
way, here's the גמרא I was quoting in קידושין, Kiddushin, it's about
כיבוד אב ואם. kibbud av va'em. And כיצד, keitzad, היה אומר דבר
שמועה מפי אביו haya omer davar shemua mipi aviv in the name
of your of your father, לא יאמר כך אמר אבא lo yomar
kach amar Abba but אלא כך אמר אבא מרי. ela kach amar
Abba Mori. הריני, Hareini, I'm sorry, this is after he dies, okay,
it says you have to be מכבדו בחייו ומכבדו במותו. mechabdo bechayav
umechabdo bemoto. במותו כיצד, Bemoto keitzad, היה אומר דבר שמועה מפי אביו
לא יאמר כך אמר אבא אלא כך אמר אבא מרי הריני כפרת
משכבו. haya omer davar shemua mipi aviv lo yomar kach amar Abba
ela kach amar Abba Mori hareini kaparat mishkavo. Okay, so specifically the
גמרא gives it in the context of when you're quoting a כיבוד
אב kibbud av and when you're quoting a הלכה halacha in his
name, which is exactly the context of our גמרא, quoting a הלכה
halacha of רבי חייא ובניו הריני כפרת משכבו. Rabbi Chiya uvanav hareini
kaparat mishkavo. And then it says והני מילי תוך שנים עשר חודש,
vehanei mili toch shenem asar chodesh, מכאן ואילך mikan va'eilach אומר זכרונו
לברכה לחיי העולם הבא. omer zichrono livracha lechayei ha'olam haba. Okay, so
during the first twelve months, which is the idea that the נשמה
neshama is judged to fit in the first twelve months, so you
are trying to help achieve the atonement of his soul during that
period of time. Which would mean that presumably ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
was saying this within, although it says רבי חייא ובניו, Rabbi Chiya
uvanav, they didn't all die within twelve months so it's a little
bit interesting that he uses that phrase. So the גמרא only says
it, so it's only first twelve months. The גמרא only says it
by כיבוד אב, kibbud av, but you know interesting I think that
it's brought down by כיבוד אם kibbud em as well, but the
גמרא brings ברבי beRabbi as well because it very much also has
it in the context of quoting a דבר הלכה dvar halacha מפי.
mipi. Okay, what's the idea of the twelve months, isn't that post-settlement?
What? The idea of twelve months of קדיש? Kaddish? But I think
of the twelve months of the, you could be right, you could
be that twelve months here is not specifically because of the idea
of the נשמה neshama being judged but it could be because like
the whole idea of twelve months is the period of אבילות aveilus
for אביו ואמו aviv ve'imo and that's particularly based on like, you
know. The פוסקים poskim say why is it that you have a
longer אבלות aveilus period for a parent and for like a spouse,
I mean people most or a child חס ושלום, chas v'shalom, and
they say it's not really because of the question of how much
you mourn over them as is different but the מצוה mitzva of
כיבוד אב ואם kibbud av v'eim demands a res- exactly כיבוד kibbud
which is what extends it to the 12 months, so that this
is in the context of כיבוד אב ואם. kibbud av v'eim. So
you're probably right, I was probably being anachronistic. It could be very
well understood that the 12 months is not because of this דין
גיהנום din Gehennom idea but just the but that's the that's the
heightened period of כיבוד אב ואם, kibbud av v'eim, so it's during
that period. Okay. All right. Well, I guess that will end for
this now. Okay, we'll pick up with the second פרק perek tomorrow.
Okay. So only specifically if you're quoting a הלכה halacha and then
Well, that's I have to check it in the in the שלחן
ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. That's how it is in the גמרא. That's what
I was telling you like one month ago. What? Yeah, everybody else
is one month. Which you you mean like brother and sister and
mother too? Yeah, it's it's only parents that it extends to twelve
months. I was at the I was at the לויה levaya for
for יצחק טברסקי, Yitzhak Twersky, זכרונו לברכה. zichrono livracha. Every other line
that his son was doing the הספד hesped was every other line
"הרי אני כפרת משכבו". Harei ani kaparas mishkavo Yeah, there's something you
do for Yeah, for the first twelve months when they're still in
the Oh. Yeah. So you mean specifically his his נשמה neshama to
get out of גיהנום? Gehennom? Exactly. They're in the process of them
trying to come back to the עולם olam which is hard. Oh.
I see a business plan that's developing in your questions. He needs
the visa. Someone already reached these things. It's getting so complicated. I
mean they've been working on the visa for six months now. Right
now they're waiting on some form from the Israeli embassy that says
that he's like not a pedophile or something and that might take
another six weeks. So there is a chance actually that there some
kind of criminal thing that Israel has to certify. But there's a
chance actually that the company he's working for in Australia would be
happy to have him work in the Boston office. They can pay
him through Israel. While that all works out he could get paid
through Israel and that would that would get him here sooner. What
does he do? He's a software like project manager for medical software.
I mean he won't have a problem finding
a job here,
it's just the visa issue. It'll make my life
a lot simpler for שושנה Shoshana not flying
to
Australia I can tell you that. So I'm hoping they
get their act together and the visa goes through. Yeah, Australia is
So some some news actually.
Okay. That's
why I might suggest this. You here for how long?
Going back today?
Yeah, I'm
going back.
All right. Safe trip back. So where where your דרשות droshes didn't
go is how important the synagogue is today. Yeah, to some exactly.
Exactly. And it's important in the context of of the שול shul
we go to in Pittsburgh which is struggling with huge debt of
a building that we can't afford.
Huh. Which שול shul is that? בית שלום. Beth Shalom.
There's a contingent that says we should sell the building and move
into a more I mean, 40 years ago there were like 2,000
families, now there's like 500. Oh wow. It's just a huge שול.
shul.
Yeah, that is the big question.
How much a synagogue is People who grew up there say no
and people who want to make sure it's still there in 20
years say yes.
Hmm.
Part of selling the air rights or something.
They're actually being very creative I have to say.
They've been more flexible than I expected them and they're looking at
lots of
options.
Someone has been even thinking of turning it
into a spa and giving
the members ten percent for a
massage every day.
That is brilliant. I somehow think that the רבנים rabbanim will be
opposed to that. They'll feel that it's like No. Did you ever
see Did you ever see this movie called זוהרה? Zohara? Or
It was made by since from this, you know, Israel they have
like מעלות, Ma'alot, it's like, you know, these, so this was like
I think one of the first movies made by it and it
was made about like the מקוה Mikvah and was made by a
woman who had like, you know, she was no longer דתיה, Datia,
she, you know, she had been דתיה, Datia, and she had had
like traumatic experiences because in Israel it's terrible, you know, the way
that they have the מקוה Mikvah ladies like giving you everybody the
third degree and it's like it's very, it's not so aesthetic. Anyway,
so there were moments which were, you know, which were like more
positive, but it was mostly through a critical lens. Anyway, but there
was this hilarious scene where this like woman from Brooklyn who had
made עליה Aliyah and she said, you know, she said, when I
was, you know, we had such a beautiful מקוה Mikvah in the
states, like, you know, you go, you, you know, you take your
novel with you, you'd be sitting and talking to your friends, they
call your number, you give your number to somebody else who wants
to go home to the kids, I'm having such a good time
here. She says, here in Israel, she says, it's like a tea
bag, one dunk and
you're
out.